<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="//purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="//purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="//www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:media="//search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title><![CDATA[wdziemia]]></title><description><![CDATA[Thoughts, stories and ideas.]]></description><link>//wdziemia.github.io/</link><image><url>//wdziemia.github.io/favicon.png</url><title>wdziemia</title><link>//wdziemia.github.io/</link></image><generator>Ghost 3.40</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Dec 2020 21:29:32 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="//wdziemia.github.io/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Scraping a Feature Together]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>YQL (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yahoo!_Query_Language">Yahoo Query Language</a>) allows you to do amazing things, and has many feeds for a developer to play with. In Peak Stocks, we use it for Option Chains and it works beautifully. An additional feature that we'd thought of was expanding social media feeds. We've gotten a lot of</p>]]></description><link>//wdziemia.github.io/the-cool-kids-way-to-scrape-pages/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5fe255174e202b72753b08a0</guid><category><![CDATA[YQL]]></category><category><![CDATA[Scraping]]></category><category><![CDATA[Data]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Walter Dziemianczyk]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 12:24:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>YQL (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yahoo!_Query_Language">Yahoo Query Language</a>) allows you to do amazing things, and has many feeds for a developer to play with. In Peak Stocks, we use it for Option Chains and it works beautifully. An additional feature that we'd thought of was expanding social media feeds. We've gotten a lot of requests for twitter and thought, why not the yahoo message boards too? This is where YQL comes into play. </p><p>YQL has community tables, which aren't actual SQL tables. These "tables" are just XML files that scrape pages or using existing feeds and return a response object that is formatted to your liking. Within YQL console, these XML files are passed off a tables making it seem like your actually accessing a database. Anyway, the community tables allow anyone to create their own custom table, be it through the methods mentioned earlier. The finance message boards dont have an open API so i had to use the page scraping method. Having not a lick of experience in doing any of this, it took me a couple of hours to get it going, with countless attempts of trial and error (view the commit history, you'll see). Once i finally got some data to work with, it got easier and easier. The final XML file can be found on my GitHub <a href="https://www.blogger.com/u/1/blog/post/edit/575225956679068977/6613830476794116182#">here</a>. </p><p>The structure of the JavaScript is very simple, its a try-catch block and 2 methods. One method gets the next-page URL and the other loops through the <code>&lt;tr&gt;</code> elements within <code>&lt;tbody&gt;</code> and appends the rows to a <code>&lt;messages&gt;</code> element. </p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="//wdziemia.github.io/content/images/2020/12/image.png" class="kg-image" alt srcset="//wdziemia.github.io/content/images/size/w600/2020/12/image.png 600w, //wdziemia.github.io/content/images/size/w1000/2020/12/image.png 1000w, //wdziemia.github.io/content/images/2020/12/image.png 1241w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>Output for <code>GOOG</code></figcaption></figure><p>Within the YQL console, you can have two YQL queries to choose from:</p><pre><code class="language-SQL">SELECT * FROM messageboard WHERE symbol='GOOG';</code></pre><ul><li>The most basic YQL query, giving you page 1 of the message board.</li></ul><pre><code class="language-SQL">SELECT * FROM messageboard WHERE symbol='GOOG' AND page=$URL;</code></pre><ul><li>The second query allows you to pick which page you'd like. The page postfix is given in the initial URL request using the YQL command above (e.g. <code>page = '/mb/forumview/?&amp;bn=12b865d6-8061-30c4-86c1-40adf7076aee&amp;page=2';</code>).</li></ul><p>As it stands, the file only parses through the a message board for a particular stock, getting all the threads within it. While it does provide you the the thread link, there is no way to get a feed for that individual thread.....yet. <br><br>The next step is to create another file that handles an individual thread. This shouldn't be difficult since I have experience from creating this one. </p><p>Until next time, <br><br>W</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Temere Fitness]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>"Catchy slogan goes here"</p><p>I've been going to the gym recently and noticed that i basically do the same exercises each time. I thought to myself "Why cant there be an app that gives me a list of workouts so that I dont get any plateau effect in my routine?</p>]]></description><link>//wdziemia.github.io/temere-fitness-catchy-slogan-goes-here/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5fe2505f4e202b72753b080c</guid><category><![CDATA[Concept]]></category><category><![CDATA[YQL]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Walter Dziemianczyk]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2013 14:32:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>"Catchy slogan goes here"</p><p>I've been going to the gym recently and noticed that i basically do the same exercises each time. I thought to myself "Why cant there be an app that gives me a list of workouts so that I dont get any plateau effect in my routine?" I looked around the play store but couldn't find anything. One app would make me pay for predefined routines while others where just a stew of text and gradients. Some apps only provided workouts for a single muscle group. What is an android developer to do?<br><br>Well, I started off with a very basic idea in my head and worked from there. The current goal is to get something simple out and then grow it into something beautiful. <br>The first small step was a name. Something with the words gym rat, random, and android. The word temere is none of those, perfect! (but seriously, any suggestions are appreciated!).</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//wdziemia.github.io/content/images/2020/12/ic_launcher.png" class="kg-image" alt></figure><p>The next small step is the launcher icon. I saw a gym-rat badge and made it android-esque. I like the icon as its simple and gives the user a basic idea of what the app is about. It will probably change as id like to change the name but it'll do for now. Id also like to follow design guidelines and make it 3D, in due time i suppose. <br></p><p>Onto the bigger stuff, interface design. The first step was thinking how the app functions. There are three things it needs to do:</p><ul><li>Step 1.) Activity : Allow a user to set what workouts they do and when</li><li>Step 2.) FragmentActivity : Exercises :<br>			- Fragment: List of exercise<br>			- Fragment: Detail view on an exercise</li></ul><p>Basic Functionality: ✅. I tend to shoot straight to creation of high-fidelity models as I can usually picture wireframes in my head. Without further adieu:</p><figure class="kg-card kg-gallery-card kg-width-wide"><div class="kg-gallery-container"><div class="kg-gallery-row"><div class="kg-gallery-image"><img src="//wdziemia.github.io/content/images/2020/12/temre_main.png" width="721" height="1280" alt srcset="//wdziemia.github.io/content/images/size/w600/2020/12/temre_main.png 600w, //wdziemia.github.io/content/images/2020/12/temre_main.png 721w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></div><div class="kg-gallery-image"><img src="//wdziemia.github.io/content/images/2020/12/temre_exercises-1.png" width="721" height="1280" alt srcset="//wdziemia.github.io/content/images/size/w600/2020/12/temre_exercises-1.png 600w, //wdziemia.github.io/content/images/2020/12/temre_exercises-1.png 721w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></div><div class="kg-gallery-image"><img src="//wdziemia.github.io/content/images/2020/12/temre_exercise_detail-1.png" width="721" height="1280" alt srcset="//wdziemia.github.io/content/images/size/w600/2020/12/temre_exercise_detail-1.png 600w, //wdziemia.github.io/content/images/2020/12/temre_exercise_detail-1.png 721w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></div></div></div></figure><p></p><p>I went with something as simple as possible and i think it looks very nice. The two things that stick out are <a href="https://www.blogger.com/u/1/blog/post/edit/575225956679068977/5483640293458952674#">chips</a> and SVG images. The chips are possible via my own version of <a href="https://www.blogger.com/u/1/blog/post/edit/575225956679068977/5483640293458952674#">chips-edittext-library</a> and SVG support is brought to you by <a href="https://www.blogger.com/u/1/blog/post/edit/575225956679068977/5483640293458952674#">svg-android</a>.</p><!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>I went with something as simple as possible and i think it looks very nice. The two things that stick out are chips and SVG images. The chips are possible via my own version of chips-edittext-library and SVG support is brought to you by svg-android<sup class="footnote-ref"><a href="#fn1" id="fnref1">[1]</a></sup>.</p>
<p>The reason for picking SVG images is because I could scale them, regardless of the screen density. SVGView[Name pending] will be created by myself as i dont know any open source components that can do this currently.</p>
<hr class="footnotes-sep">
<section class="footnotes">
<ol class="footnotes-list">
<li id="fn1" class="footnote-item"><p>If your saving from illustrator, make sure you save as SVG Basic 1.1. Also, when creating your document, dont mess around with the art-boards after as it will mess with how the library reads the files. <a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-backref">↩︎</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown--><p>That its so far! I'll be going into detail with how each functions once I get done with them. I also plan on making this project available on GitHub once its released on the play store. Stay tuned and comments/feedback are greatly appreciated. I'd love any constructive criticism I can get.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Facebook Concept]]></title><description><![CDATA[<figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//wdziemia.github.io/content/images/2020/12/tumblr_mdxip5mb2d1rlhttno1_r1_1280.png" class="kg-image" alt srcset="//wdziemia.github.io/content/images/size/w600/2020/12/tumblr_mdxip5mb2d1rlhttno1_r1_1280.png 600w, //wdziemia.github.io/content/images/size/w1000/2020/12/tumblr_mdxip5mb2d1rlhttno1_r1_1280.png 1000w, //wdziemia.github.io/content/images/2020/12/tumblr_mdxip5mb2d1rlhttno1_r1_1280.png 1280w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>The concept is more inline with the Facebook webpage than the Facebook app. The current Facebook app does not keep to the UX offered with the Facebook website. This idea is what puzzles me the most when creating a mobile application. When going from web to mobile, the user (already</p>]]></description><link>//wdziemia.github.io/facebook-concept/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5fe254774e202b72753b0893</guid><category><![CDATA[Concept]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Walter Dziemianczyk]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2013 13:29:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="//wdziemia.github.io/content/images/2020/12/tumblr_mdxip5mb2d1rlhttno1_r1_1280.png" class="kg-image" alt srcset="//wdziemia.github.io/content/images/size/w600/2020/12/tumblr_mdxip5mb2d1rlhttno1_r1_1280.png 600w, //wdziemia.github.io/content/images/size/w1000/2020/12/tumblr_mdxip5mb2d1rlhttno1_r1_1280.png 1000w, //wdziemia.github.io/content/images/2020/12/tumblr_mdxip5mb2d1rlhttno1_r1_1280.png 1280w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>The concept is more inline with the Facebook webpage than the Facebook app. The current Facebook app does not keep to the UX offered with the Facebook website. This idea is what puzzles me the most when creating a mobile application. When going from web to mobile, the user (already familiar with the webpage) shouldn't be greeted with an entirely new experience. Some familiarity should be help which lacks with Facebook's current approach.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Welcome]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>This Blog will be about Android stuff, enjoy the Android stuff!</p>]]></description><link>//wdziemia.github.io/welcome/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5fe24f284e202b72753b0801</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Walter Dziemianczyk]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jun 2012 14:59:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This Blog will be about Android stuff, enjoy the Android stuff!</p>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>